Feinstein International Center Records UA197
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
- White papers, UA197.000267
  - Livelihoods and Nutrition of Marginalized People, 2000 -- 2011; UA197.012; 24 Digital Object(s)
    - Coping with War, Coping with Peace: Livelihood Adaptation in Bosnia-Herzegovina, 1989-2004, 2005-04-13; UA197.012.012.00011; Stites, Elizabeth; Lautze, Sue; Mazurana, Dyan; Anic, Alma
      This study uses a livelihood framework to examine and analyze household livelihood strategies across three time periods in six rural villages in Bosnia-Herzegovina. The three time periods examined are the ending of the Cold War (1989), the height of the Conflict, Armed (War), and late 2004. The study focuses on the ways in which households adapted their livelihood strategies to respond to drastic changes in access to assets, shifts in coping strategies, and the resulting livelihood outcomes as they experienced changes in their political, social, and economic environment.
      Conflict, Armed (War); Economies and societies in transition; Feinstein International Center
    - Filling the Blue Box: Mutuelles, Self-financing and Financial Services in the South of Haiti, 2008-02-13; UA197.012.012.00012; Wilson, Kim; Burpee, Gaye
      In Haiti, many farmers lie beyond the reach of the formal banking system and MFIs. A powerful method of local financial intermediation, called mutuelles is helping to bridge the gap. Efficiently formed by local NGOs and church organizations, mutuelles are forces of social change. They also demonstrate financial discipline and could prove an interesting market for MFIs and banks seeking new customers for financial services.
    - Bolivia: Drought, Food Insecurity And Marginalization, 2000-02-07; UA197.012.012.00013; Sarmiento, Juan Pablo
      Before the 1990's, professionals working in the emergency and disaster field saw disaster management as the ultimate goal to achieve. Their focus was on identifying hazards and taking measures to minimize the impact of a disaster. At this time, there were two main types of organizations working in the field. On the one-hand, you had scientific and technical organizations analyzing the disaster and its impact, and on the other, there were relief agencies, health services, public works, the military and other logistical organizations addressing the needs of the people affected by the disaster.
    - Human Security and Livelihoods of Rural Afghans (Dari), 2004-10-14; UA197.012.012.00014; Mazurana, Dyan; Stites, Elizabeth; Nojumi, Neamat
      This report (in Dari translation) documents and analyzes recent countrywide trends in the relationship between human security and livelihoods throughout rural Afghanistan from 2002-2003. All countrywide information is generated by analyses of 2003 Nationwide Risk and Vulnerability Assessment (NRVA) survey data. All analyses of NRVA data, unless otherwise noted, are conducted by the Tufts University team. In addition, the report includes detailed analyses on six provinces based on primary research by the Tufts team in Badghis, Balkh, Herat, Kabul, Kandahar, and Nangarhar.
      Economic conditions; Feinstein International Center
    - Livelihoods Mapping to Understand Humanitarian Impact - Balkans, 2004-07-01; UA197.012.012.00015; Lautze, Sue; Raven Roberts, Angela
      The objective of the fieldwork is to test the utility of the Livelihoods Initiatives Program's modified livelihoods framework (see Figure 1, below) for mapping livelihoods system in conflict-affected settings. Field work will commence with the identification of research partners in June/July, 2004 and continue through January, 2005.
    - Nutrition and Livelihoods: In Situations of Conflict and other Crises: Reducing Vulnerability And Risk, 2002-11-12; UA197.012.012.00016; Young, Helen; Aklilu, Yacob; Were, George; Catley, Andy; Leyland, Tim; Borrel, Annalies; Raven Roberts, Angela; Webb, Patrick; Holland, Diane; Johnecheck, Wendy
      This paper describes three types of livelihood interventions aimed at supporting and protecting pastoralist systems of production. This generates a preliminary set of essential principles underlying a livelihoods approach in emergency contexts. These relate to: assessment and analyses; prioritising and combining response strategies; and combining appropriate technical skills, including public nutrition, together with local knowledge in implementing programmes. The paper concludes with an agenda for learning and applied research with particular emphasis on nutrition livelihoods linkages.
    - Reducing Vulnerability through Livelihoods Promotion in Shelter Sector Activities: An Initial Examination for Potential Mitigation and Post-Disaster Application, 2001-09-24; UA197.012.012.00017; Setchell, Charles A.
      Shelter improvements and provision can assume a leading role in promoting both household livelihoods and community recovery in disasteraffected areas. Livelihoods promotion in shelter sector activities can also serve as a primary means of reducing the vulnerability of communities to disasters.
      Human settlements; Feinstein International Center
    - Addressing Livelihoods in Afghanistan, 2002-01-01; UA197.012.012.00018; Pain, Adam; Lautze, Sue
      This paper has two core objectives. The first is to build a critical understanding of the concept of livelihoods in Afghanistan. The second is to investigate the way livelihood issues are being addressed in the policy and programming processes of Afghanistan's humanitarian and reconstruction agenda.
    - Livelihood Interventions in Conflict-Affected Areas: Dilemmas & Lessons Learned, 2003-05-23; UA197.012.012.00019; Feinstein International Center
      The Feinstein International Famine Center is committed to the Sphere process (which seeks to establish standards and guidelines for NGO practices in the humanitarian field), and the timing of the workshop offered the opportunity to contribute to the revision process of the Sphere Food Security minimum standards which is currently underway. One of the tasks of the workshop was therefore to review the draft Sphere Food Security minimum standards to determine if microfinance initiatives are adequately addressed, so that Sphere key indicators and guidance notes could be revised accordingly.
      Food security; Humanitarian Assistance; Non-governmental organizations; Feinstein International Center
    - Loaves and Fishes: Famine Challenges in the New Millennium, 2004-03-26; UA197.012.012.00020; Lautze, Sue
      Remarks to the Sixth Annual Conference, Global Disaster Information Network -- Session on "Challenges of Contemporary Famine"
      Famine; Food security; Food relief; Feinstein International Center
    - Qaht-E-Pool "A Cash Famine": Food Insecurity in Afghanistan 1999-2002, 2002-06-07; UA197.012.012.00021; Lautze, Sue; Stites, Elizabeth; Nojumi, Neamat; Najimi, Fazalkarim
      Food security; Humanitarian action; Feinstein International Center
    - Saving Lives and Livelihoods: The Fundamentals of a Livelihoods Strategy, 2000-02-07; UA197.012.012.00022; Lautze, Sue
      Complex emergencies are characterized, in part, by the deliberate exploitation of civilians. Undermining self-sufficiency and productivity are not merely by-products of conflict, but also are the intended consequences of war. In complex emergencies, systems of production are particularly vulnerable, rendering these types of disasters fundamentally different from natural disasters. Consequently, innovative approaches to providing relief and recovery assistance are essential. Tools for analyzing the critical trade-offs between implementing more immediate survival interventions and fostering self-sufficiency to ensure longer-term survival, i.e., saving lives and livelihoods, are much-needed by the international humanitarian relief community.
      Humanitarian Assistance; Conflict, Armed (War); Feinstein International Center
    - Community Case Management of Severe Acute Malnutrition in Southern Bangladesh, 2011-10-18; UA197.012.012.00023; Sadler, Kate; Puett, Chloe; Mothabbit, Golam; Myatt, Mark
      Bangladesh has the fourth-highest number of children around 600,000 at any one time suffering from severe acute malnutrition (SAM) in the world. This prospective cohort study examined the effectiveness and feasibility of adding the diagnosis and treatment of SAM to the community case management package delivered by community health workers outside health facilities in Barisal, Bangladesh.
      Children; Nutrition; Feinstein International Center
    - Achieving Food and Nutrition Security: Lessons Learned from the Integrated Food Security Programme (IFSP), Mulanje, Malawi, 2011-06-16; UA197.012.012.00024; Webb, Patrick
      Calls have been made recently for new approaches to the design and implementation of interventions aimed at achieving household food security; approaches that address more than just food availability by integrating actions enhancing food access and utilization as well. But what exactly should be integrated and how? This report represents a lessons learned assessment of an integrated agriculture, nutrition, and health intervention implemented in Malawi in the late 1990s and early 2000s. The review contributes to the ongoing international search for best practices in programming for food security. The Integrated Food Security Programme (IFSP) was designed as a self-reinforcing, synergistic program implemented in an area of extreme food insecurity. Nevertheless, the endline evaluation in 2004 reported that the intervention had achieved most of its aims. Child nutrition was improved (reaching the target set of a 10% reduction in the prevalence of stunting), and most sectoral targets in agriculture, income generating, and infrastructure development were also achieved. At roughly US$59 per household per year, the cost of the package of interventions integrated on the ground compares well with a range of other integrated programs in Malawi and elsewhere in the world. Importantly, many of the gains have been sustained.
      Food security; Nutrition; Feinstein International Center
  - The Evolving Global Environment of Crisis and Crisis Response, 2000 -- 2011; UA197.013; 11 Digital Object(s)
    This series contains reports related to The Evolving Global Environment of Crisis and Crisis Response project.
    - State-building, Counterterrorism, and Licensing Humanitarianism in Somalia, 2010-10-12; UA197.013.013.00001; Bradbury, Mark
      The people of Somalia have experienced two decades of humanitarian crisis. In 1992, in the wake of the collapse of the Somali state, Somalia set a benchmark for humanitarian crises in the immediate post-Cold War world, with a war and famine that killed a quarter of a million people and displaced over 3 million more. Two decades later, Somalia once again is being described as one of the worst humanitarian crises in the world, with over 1.5 million people internally displaced and over half a million Somalis living as refugees in neighboring countries. At the same time, as the Conflict, Armed (War) has increasingly taken on a regional and international dimension access for humanitarian agencies has become extremely restricted.
    - Iraq: more challenges ahead for a fractured humanitarian enterprise, 2009-02-02; UA197.013.013.00002; Hansen, Greg
      The report draws upon five years of active monitoring in Iraq and the region, a relatively long period in which agencies have had many opportunities to adapt to a difficult context. The author argues that despite some improvements in security for Iraqis, the ability of the international community to provide for the most vulnerable is impaired by the continued politicization of humanitarian response and systemic deficiencies in coordination mechanisms.
    - Humanitarianism in Sri Lanka: Lessons Learned?, 2010-07-01; UA197.013.013.00003; Harris, Simon
      This briefing paper summarizes the key issues and dynamics that have shaped the humanitarian experience in Sri Lanka and draws lessons that, if learned, may help inform humanitarian engagement in other international contexts.
      Conflict, Armed (War); Terrorism; Humanitarian Assistance; Feinstein International Center
    - Mapping the Security Environment: Understanding the perceptions of local communities, peace support operations, and assistance agencies, 2005-06-13; UA197.013.013.00004; Donini, Antonio; Minear, Larry; Smillie, Ian; van Baarda, Ted; Welch, Anthony C.
      The data presented and analyzed by the study in three cases-Afghanistan, Kosovo, and Sierra Leone-offers intriguing and provocative look at the wide-ranging security needs of local communities and the uneven extent to which these are understood and responded to by major international institutions. The voices of local communities are not being heard, much less "priviledged", by outside actors. The dominant voices in transition environments instead are those of peace support operations (PSOs) and assistance agencies (AAs). Even the voice of government is often muffled. Such a disconnect has major implications: if the perceptions of local communities were to be the entry point for outside actor engagement or the benchmark for the effectiveness of international assistance and peace support, a major re-thinking of the ways PSOs and AA's operate would be required.
    - Complexity and Context as the Determinants of the Future, 2008-07-28; UA197.013.013.00005; Walker, Peter
      Humanitarian crises today are not due to one underlying cause but rather to a set of complex issues or an accumulation of adverse trends.
    - Humanitarian Action in Pakistan 2005-2010: Challenges, Principles, and Politics, 2011-02-06; UA197.013.013.00006; PÌ©chayre, Marion
      Over the past five years, Pakistan has witnessed three major crises affecting up to 18 million people. The nature and scale of these crises were different. Two were disasters caused by natural hazards: the 2005 earthquake (affecting 3.5 million people) and the 2010 floods (affecting more than 20 million people). The 2008-2010 Internally Displaced People (IDP) crisis was triggered by an internal conflict and displaced 4.2 million people from the Khyber Pakhtunkhwa (KPK) and Federally Administered Tribal Areas (FATA). Facing these different and significant crises in such a short period of time, humanitarian actors had to adapt rapidly and faced dilemmas that were new to them in the context of Pakistan. This paper examines the impact of the three above-mentioned crises on the evolution of the humanitarian system and its ability to respond to emergencies in Pakistan since 2005. It follows a chronological order, looking first at the legacy of the 2005 earthquake response on the humanitarian system, and second at the influence it had on its ability to respond to the 2008-2010 IDP crisis, and finally it explores the challenges humanitarians had to face at the onset of the flood crisis.
    - Aid to Sudan's Rebels: Right Idea, Wrong Plan, 2000-02-09; UA197.013.013.00007; Lautze, Sue
      Terrorism, humanitarian and conflict-resolution issues keep Sudan a country of concern to US foreign policy makers. The amendment to the Foreign Operations Bill signed into law by President Clinton on November 29 permits the President to provide food assistance to rebel groups operating in Sudan. This policy shift signals a welcomed stance by the US indicating that the status quo in Sudan is no longer acceptable. It reflects a refreshing renewed commitment to engage with Sudan's problems. However, its formulation is deeply flawed and its implementation is ill-advised.
      Terrorism; Humanitarian Assistance; Feinstein International Center
    - Beyond Kobe: A Proactive Look at the World Conference on Disaster Reduction (18-22 January 2005, Kobe, Japan), 2005-07-30; UA197.013.013.00008; Wisner, Ben; Walker, Peter
      The World Conference on Disaster Reduction (WCDR), held in Kobe, Japan, from 18-22 January, 2005 showcased some of the best developments in disaster reduction, but inevitably many good initiatives require sustained commitments and efforts to make it from the neighborhoods and villages all over the world into the official agency and intergovernmental processes. Some fell by the wayside. This report seeks to analyze the underlying causes of continued disaster vulnerability, to showcase best practice from the field and to highlight some of the key issues emerging from the WCDR Conference at Kobe. It presents 10 key recommendations which the authors believe complement the Hyogo Framework for Action.
      Natural disasters; Feinstein International Center
    - Humanitarian Seminar Series, 2000-06-22; UA197.013.013.00009; Feinstein International Center
      Schedule for the Humanitarian Seminar Series, 1998-99
      Humanitarian Assistance; Peace-building; Feinstein International Center
    - Operational Learning Review of Libya Secondary Data Review, 2011-05-06; UA197.013.013.00010; Montgomery, Kate
      The ultimate goal of the ACAPS project is more effective, efficient and appropriate humanitarian responses to crises. The aim is to achieve this by promoting better informed and more evidence driven responses, specifically by supporting a process of coordinated needs assessment which is timely, coherent, and appropriate to context, with results that are accessible and relevant to decision?makers. This is partly prompted by donor demands for more evidence?based funding proposals, as well as for more joined up and better prioritized program strategies.
    - Sex and Age Matter, 2011-08-24; UA197.013.013.00011; Mazurana, Dyan; Benelli, Prisca; Gupta, Huma; Walker, Peter
      Humanitarian aid is largely guided by anecdotes rather than evidence. Currently, the humanitarian system shows significant weaknesses in data collection, analysis and response in all stages of a crisis or emergency. As a result, the present humanitarian system is much less evidence-driven than it should be and than it would like to be. To ensure that vulnerabilities, needs and access to life-saving services are best understood and responded to, humanitarian actors must collect information based on sex and age. When this data is lacking, it limits the effectiveness of humanitarian response in all phases of a crisis.
      Humanitarian Assistance; Children; Impact assessment; Feinstein International Center
  - Impact Assessment, 2005 -- 2011; UA197.014; 4 Digital Object(s)
    This series contains reports related to the Impact Assessment project.
    - Impact Assessment of the Zimbabwe Dams and Gardens Project, 2008-04-08; UA197.014.014.00001; Burns, John; Suji, Omeno W
      This study was an Impact assessment of the 'Zimbabwe Dams and Gardens' Project' a community based famine prevention and mitigation intervention being implemented by CARE International in Masvingo Province, Zimbabwe. The assessment is one component of a broader applied research initiative "Impact Assessment of Innovative Humanitarian Projects in Sub-Saharan Africa" supported by the Bill & Melinda (B&M) Gates Foundation. The research which is being carried out by the Feinstein International Center (FIC, Tufts) focuses on the development and application of a participatory assessment toolkit to measure the impact of seven projects in Africa being supported by the B&M Gates Foundation under a separate grant; the "Sub-Saharan Africa Famine Relief Effort". All seven projects have taken an integrated livelihoods approach to alleviating the immediate needs of the affected communities, and to addressing the longer term vulnerability issues resulting in famine and food insecurity.
    - Impact Assessment of the Pastoralist Survival and Recovery Project: Dakoro, Niger, 2005-04-28; UA197.014.014.00002; Burns, John; Suji, Omeno W; Reynolds, Alexa
      This report is the outcome of an Impact assessment of the 'Pastoralist Survival and Recovery Project' implemented by Lutheran World Relief and partners in North Dakoro, Niger. The assessment is the last of four impact studies carried out by the Feinstein Center under the "Impact Assessment of Innovative Humanitarian Projects in Sub-Saharan Africa" research initiative supported by the Bill & Melinda Gates Foundation. The 'Pastoralist Survival and Recovery Project' was designed to assist ten pastoral communities living in the Tarka Valley recover from the effects of a prolonged drought, culminating in locust attacks and a failed harvest in 2004. The project also aimed to enhance the capacity of pastoral communities to cope with the effects of future droughts and other shocks by ensuring year round access to food and income. The main project activities included the establishment of six Livestock feed banks, restocking of small ruminants, and the construction of four wells for both human and Livestock utilization. The impact study focused on the re-stocking and animal feed bank project interventions, and set out to assess what changes in household Food security and income had occurred as a result of the project. The study also looked at how the re-stocking activities might have potentially improved participants resilience to future droughts and other shocks. The assessment was carried out by project staff from Lutheran World Relief and Contribution `a l'Education de Base, and supported by a consultant from Lutheran World Relief and a consultant and a research assistant from the Feinstein International Center.
      Pastoral systems; Feinstein International Center
    - Impact Assessment of the Chical Integrated Recovery Action Project, Niger, 2008-03-31; UA197.014.014.00003; Burns, John; Suji, Omeno W
      This report is the outcome of an Impact assessment of the 'Chical Integrated Recovery Action Project' an integrated livelihoods and drought mitigation intervention implemented by Africare in the Tillaberi region of Niger. The assessment is one component of a broader applied research initiative "Impact Assessment of Innovative Humanitarian Projects in Sub-Saharan Africa" supported by the Bill & Melinda Gates Foundation. The 'Chical Integrated Recovery Action Project' was designed to assist ten communities to cope with and recover from the effects of an ongoing food crisis triggered by a failed harvest in 2004.
    - Impact Assessment of the Gokwe Integrated Recovery Action Project, 2008-01-22; UA197.014.014.00004; Burns, John; Suji, Omeno W
      This study was an Impact assessment of the "Gokwe Integrated Recovery Action Project" (GIRA) a drought recovery and famine mitigation intervention being implemented by Africare in the Midlands Province of Zimbabwe. The assessment is one component of a broader applied research initiative "Impact Assessment of Innovative Humanitarian Projects in Sub-Saharan Africa" supported by the Bill & Melinda (B&M) Gates Foundation. The research which is being carried out by the Feinstein International Center (FIC, Tufts) focuses on the development and application of a participatory assessment toolkit to measure the impact of seven projects in Africa being supported by the B&M Gates Foundation under a separate grant; the "Sub-Saharan Africa Famine Relief Effort". All seven projects have taken an integrated livelihoods approach to alleviating the immediate needs of the affected communities, and to addressing the longer term vulnerability issues resulting in famine and food insecurity.
    - Impact Assessments of Livelihoods-based Drought Interventions in Moyale and Dire Woredas, 2007-03-15; UA197.014.014.00005; Catley, Andrew